And similarly, we can combine multiple conditions
using the logical operators, how exactly.
So let's say I wanted to compare if, in ID,
let me just comment all of this for now.
You can play around with this later on,
the same kind of a code, just a moment.
Yeah, this is commented.
So let's say either requirement,
I said, if ID is not equal to zero, right?
Now the second condition,
rather than writing a different separative,
I could have said, and there's a variable called user,
or let's call it, is user at queue.
And I said, if ID is not equal to zero
and is user at queue equal to equal to true.
Then say, a sound, welcome user.
Okay.
Otherwise, a sound, I'll say, invalid user.
Okay. And again, you can remove the curly braces
because these are just one lines here, right?
But, and this is active.
We can obviously take it from runtime
or get it from a database in a big application later on.
But for now, let's put in a hard code of value.
I'll say, is user at queue, and I'll say it true for now.
Myself, later on, this would come from a data source
or a console, right?
So I've said that if ID is only equal to zero
and is user at queue equal to,
this is just, it says, it can be simplified of course, right?
So we can email it like this, because why not, right?
Now, why is this still a still warning?
Condition is user at queue is always true and reached.
Why? Because this is a hard coded value,
we should never take it, right?
But for the purpose of this program, we'll just stick to it.
So it says that it's not zero and the user is active.
Welcome user, otherwise invalid user.
Now, without the logical operator,
I would have been made to,
I would have been forced to write two conditions,
a nested if, right?
But here I just have used the logical operator and, right?
What does that mean?
This if is now true if both the conditions are true, right?
Only in this case, it works.
Even if one of the conditions is false,
this is considered to be false, right?
And let's just have a look at this.
See, I'll just run this and it says,
enter your ID, I says zero, see, invalid user.
It did not execute this if and went on to this.
That means both of these need to be true.
I'll say it on this again, enter one.
Welcome user because easier is active is true.
This is also true, it's not zero, it's a welcome user.
So even if one of the conditions is false, that's false, right?
Then the other operator is the or, right?
And that means either of these two conditions
should be true for this if to be considered true, right?
Unlike and because answers both should be true,
then I would consider this entire condition to be true,
but or says either one of these conditions needs to be true.
So now if you enter ID, which is not zero,
but user active would be false,
this would still be considered true.
Obviously in this kind of a requirement,
I don't need to use or because here the requirement says,
I have to use and right?
Because for this to work,
either of these conditions should be true, right?
And if both of them are true, it's still true.
And when does this fail, when both the conditions are false,
then this if is considered to be a false, right?
So and on the other hand,
I can also use singular and singular.
This is still a logical operator,
but this time it's a non short circuit and this is a slightly
lesser effective version of the logical and why?
Because it says again, for this if to be considered true,
both the conditions should be true,
that is the left hand side and the right hand side,
but there is a big part here.
Now, let's say this condition was false.
I entered 10.
Oh, sorry, I entered zero, right?
Obviously now this if cannot be true
because no matter if this is true or false,
this has turned out to be false.
This if is a false because and says both the conditions
have to be true, right?
But this still goes on and evaluates the second condition
less efficient making it less efficient, right?
Because this is still going to be false,
but if this was a logical operator that is short circuit
and that means if the first condition was false,
it would not even evaluate the second condition
because no matter if it is true or false,
this is still going to be false.
It just moves on and goes through the else.
That's why this short circuit and is more effective.
But in certain situations,
you want it to still evaluate the second condition.
That's why there is the stool in the language,
the non short circuit hand.
And similarly, we have the short circuit or
and the non short circuit or and this works like,
if the first condition is true,
now even if it's false, the condition works, right?
But it still goes on and evaluates it, right?
So this is the difference between short circuit and
and short circuit or and here obviously I know
I have to use the short circuit and right?
And then I have the not as well,
which unlike a logical operator and an or,
it can only be used with one condition
and just makes the inverse, the reverse of a condition.
I say for example, if ID equal to equal to 90,
do something, but if you use not here,
it just inverses the complete condition, right?
Or for example, if I would have said,
if ID is less than or equal to 90,
let's say this was my requirement, right?
So you would just put in a not here and it would have worked
like this and it was, that's it.
What does it say in the morning?
Remember yellow is a warning.
It says if statement has empty body,
why are you writing it?
We know it's empty obviously.
We want to put something significant there.
But for now, just making you understand this is a not.
Now see, if there was not a not here,
so you would have said if ID equal to or less than equal to 90,
that is if ID was 87, this would have worked.
But now it does the inverse, right?
Now this needs to be greater than 90 for this to be worked.
And sometimes you have a requirement of using what?
So this was using the if and the else with the comparison
operators and the logical operators as well.
So again, depending on your requirement,
you would use any one of them.
And I'll just put in some exercises after this video
so that you have good hands-on on using.
And you can think about when to use which kind of operator
member of my lines that is a requirement is always as is always.
So it's not requirement, programming is always a requirement.